Guide to the Melanie Kaye/Kantrowitz Papers TAM.824
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series III. Events and Appearances, 1974-2008; 3 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 oversized flat box, and 2 shared boxes.; 1 audiocassette
  - Speech -- "To Change the Way Racism is Fought", undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Workshop Script on Racism, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Texas Speech -- "Women and Israel: Whose Promised Land?", undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Talk Re: Self-Hate, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - WRAC Speech, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - National Women's Studies Association -- "NWSA Struggle" Speech, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Events and Appearances -- Promotional Fliers, Posters, 1983-2008 (Box 7, Folder 13-16, Box 35, Folder 4)
- Series IV. Journals, Notebooks, and Datebooks, 1970s-2009; 9 Linear Feet in 18 manuscript boxes.
  This series includes Kaye/Kantrowitz's typed and handwritten daily journals, notebooks, and datebooks from the 1970s to 2009. Journal daily accounts provide insight into her personal life as a lesbian and Jewish woman during the 1970s to 2010s, while also dovetailing with her work as a professor, writer, and activist. The journals in this series also include portions of letters, creative writings, and recountings of her dreams. Her creative writings were often influenced and inspired by events in her life, pulled from her journals. These journals bring context to her published works in Series I. The notebooks in this series contain writing ideas, to do lists, and contact lists. Datebooks include her daily appointements dating from 1979 to 2009. Her passport from circa 1975 is also in this series, documenting her travel during this time.
  - Journal Entries, Notes, and Writings, 1970s (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
  - Passport, circa 1975 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Journals and Notes, 1976-1978 (Box 13, Folder 6-16, Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Diaries and Journals, 1978-1980 (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 4-9)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1979-1984 (Box 18, Folder 10-11)
  - Datebooks, Address Books, 1979-2009 (Box 32, Folder 7, Box 33, Folder 1-7, Box 34, Folder 1-16)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 12-16, Box 19, Folder 1-6)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1981-January 1982 (Box 19, Folder 7-13)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1982-1983 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1983-1984 (Box 20, Folder 7, Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1984-1986 (Box 21, Folder 3-5, Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1987-1988 (Box 22, Folder 2-18)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1988-April 1990 (Box 23, Folder 1-15)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, May-December 1990 (Box 24, Folder 1-13)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1990-1993 (Box 25, Folder 1-15)
  - Journals, Notes, Writings, 1992-1993 (Box 26, Folder 1-10)
  - Journals and Notebooks, 1994-1995 (Box 27, Folder 1-6)
  - Journals and Notebooks, 1995-1997 (Box 28, Folder 1-7)
  - Journals and Notebooks, 1997-2001 (Box 29, Folder 1-6)
  - Journals and Notebooks, 1999-2001 (Box 30, Folder 1-7)
  - Journals and Notebooks, 2001-2005 (Box 31, Folder 1-7)
  - Notebooks, 2006-2009 (Box 32, Folder 1-3)
  - Diary Entries, Loose Notes, Song Notebook, undated (Box 32, Folder 4-6)
- Series V. Jews for Racial and Economic Justice (JFREJ), 1992-2006; 1 linear foot in 2 manuscript boxes.
  This series includes JFREJ promotional and communications material from the 1990s and 2000s while Kaye/Kantrowitz was a founding director and active member. Publications include the Bulletin and The JFREJ Broadside. This series also contains organization brochures and press releases; press clippings; event fliers; and workshop material. Programs and promotional material for the Rabbi Marshall T. Meyer Risk-Taker Awards and the In Struggle In Gerangl Festival and Events are also in this series.
  - Bulletin, 1992-1998 (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - Informational Brochures, Fliers, Press Releases, Press Clippings, 1992-1999 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - In Struggle In Gerangl Festival and Events -- Programs, 1995-1998, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Kaye/Kantrowitz Resignation Letter and Speech Text, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Events -- Promotional Materials, Programs, 1995-2006 (Box 17, Folder 4-5)
  - Rabbi Marshall T. Meyer Risk-Taker Awards -- Programs, 1996-2007 (Box 17, Folder 6-7)
  - Public Education Statements, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Working Group and Board-Related Material, circa 1999 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - The JFREJ Broadside, 1999-2002, 2007 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Anti-Arab Working Group Material, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - COJ Contracts List, circa 2006 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Anti-bias Workshop Material, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Anti-Semitism Workshop Material, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Series VI. Correspondence, 1973-2015, undated; 3 Linear Feet in 6 manuscript boxes.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by last name, followed by folders grouped by decade in chronological order.
  This series includes correspondence with Kaye/Kantrowitz's friends, romantic partners, colleagues, and family dating from the 1970s to 2010s. These letters express Kaye/Kantrowitz's thoughts and feelings regarding relationships, work, activism, and general news. A small collection of letters with her sister Roni Natov and her mother and father are in this series dating from the 1970s to 1990s. Correspondence from 1982 to 1989 with her co-editor Irena Klepfisz relates to their work on the book The Tribe of Dina: A Jewish Women's Anthology. Notes and letters from writer Adrienne Rich in this series discuss projects and common friends, dating from 1982 to 1993.
  - Blanchard, Margaret, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clarke, Cheryl, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Cliff, Michelle, 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Colandrea, Marie, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - "Paula and Diane", 1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Fan Mail, 1990-1993 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Jacobus, Sarah, 1991-1993 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Kellman, Ellen, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Kesselman, Amy, 1980-1983 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Klepfisz, Irena, 1982-1989 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Lucas, Dino, 1979-1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Luisi, Michaele, 1978-1991 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Re: Middle East, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Mordecai, Page, 1991-1993 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Mother and Father, 1973-1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Natov, Roni, 1981-1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - New Jewish Agenda, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Nim, Naomi, 1991-1995 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Nowicki, Diane, 1979-1996 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - O'Neill, Maureen, 1991-1993 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
  - Ordover, Nancy, 1993-1996 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Rich, Adrienne, 1982-1993 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Rosenblum, Barbara, 1985-1989 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Sheldon Ranz-Related, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Sigel, Gwynne, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Smith, Barbara, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Vance, Linda, 1987-1992 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Walker, Shannon, 1997-1998 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 12, Folder 3-5)
  - 2000s-2010s and Undated, 2000s-2010s, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-2)